Hello everyone and welcome to
English pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and
today we are cleaning right Marco.
That's right today we
are cleaning our house,
it's not one of our
favorite activities
but we have to do it and so
we're going to take a look at a
lot of great vocab related to,
you know, household chores.
That's right so let's take a
listen to today's dialogue.
What is this mess?
It looks like a pigsty
in here, clean this up.
Okay dad, I will do it in a minute, let
me just finish this level of this game.
No I said now, plus you are grounded,
you're not allowed to play video games.
I want you to make
your bed, do the laundry
and then come downstairs
and sweep the floors.
That's so unfair.
You have to pull your way around
here young man, my house, my rules.
But I already mopped the floors,
dusted the furniture and vacuum the rugs.
That's great but you still
have work to do so get to it.
So today on language takeaway
let's take a look at all the
verbs and all the ways that
we have to clean the house.
So starting with the first one we
have to make the bed, make your bed.
Make your bed, okay
so this might sound quite
strange because the
verb to make is something
we say for a lot of
different things like
make a deal, make a
mistake, make a mistake.
And here we're making the bed, that means
we're putting the pillows on top of the bed
and we're going to make
sure the blanket is even.
So when you get out
of bed, if everything is
very messy, when you make
it, you put everything in order.
That's right.
And it's also confusing because
our next verb is to do the laundry.
All right so you make your
bed but you do the laundry.
The laundry here means
you clean the dirty clothes.
So this is one of the very I would say
confusing parts of English where it's kind of
confusing when to use the verb
make, when to use the verb do.
So usually you make a mistake as we say or
you make a cake but you do your homework.
So it's just in these cases
you just kind of have to
memorize that you make the
bed but you do the laundry.
Exactly.
So this is very common
actually to do the laundry.
I have to go do the laundry
today because it's an event.
You know you have to
gather your clothes and
put in the detergent
and wash it and dry it.
So just remember make the bed, do the laundry
but then how do we clean those floors?
All right.
So the floor we have to do two things.
We sweep the floors.
So the verb there is to
sweep and how do you sweep?
You actually use a broom to sweep.
So the broom is like
a straw, it's like a brush
almost, you use on
the floor and you collect
all of the hair and the dust and these
things and you put it into the garbage bin.
But after you sweep
then you need to use
water to clean because
obviously sleeping is
just for dry things, mopping is actually
how you clean with water and soap.
That's right.
So the verb there is
to mop the floors and
usually you use water, you
soap and you use a mop.
So you use a mop to mop.
Exactly.
The verb is to mop.
The noun, the object is a mop like you say.
So I'm going to mop the floors, right?
So please don't come
into the kitchen, right?
Okay.
And well, now we need
to clean the furniture
and usually on the furniture
we have a lot of dust.
So we need to dust the
furniture, too dust, too dust.
Yeah, this is something
we don't use for
the floors really because we
have this great verb to sweep.
But with furniture and
things like that, we say
to dust and this means
we're going to collect
the dust off of the piano
or the sofa or the table.
Right, exactly.
And now the floors we
clean, the furniture we
clean, but sometimes
we have rugs or we have
carpet in our house,
usually in the bedrooms
or we have a large
rug in the living room.
And we need to clean that as
well, but we don't really mop it.
We don't sweep it.
It's best to vacuum it.
All right.
So the verb is to vacuum
and what is the noun?
The thing we use?
A vacuum cleaner.
A vacuum cleaner or just simply a vacuum.
Now this is something that uses air
to suck up all of the dirt in garbage.
So it goes ah, and it sucks
up all of that bad stuff.
And so we don't have to dust it and obviously
with carpet we can't really use water.
So this is a great tool for
cleaning fabric like carpets and rugs.
That very good.
So that's all the ways that we can basically,
the verbs that we use to clean around
the house, let's listen to the dialogue
again and we'll be back in a bit.
And what is this mess?
It looks like a pig sty in here.
Clean this up.
Okay dad, I will do it in a minute.
Let me just finish this level of this game.
No, I said now.
Plus you are grounded.
You're not allowed to play video games.
I want you to make
your bed, do the laundry
and then come downstairs
and sweep the floors.
That's so unfair.
You have to pull your way around
here young man, my house, my rules.
But I already mop the floors, dusted
the furniture and vacuum the rugs.
That's great.
I've worked to do so get to it.
All right, so now let's take a look at some
phrases, three of them on Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
All right now the first
word here is pig sty.
The dad says, Kevin, it
looks like a pig sty in here.
Clean this up.
Right.
So a pig sty.
It looks like a pig sty.
Now a pig sty is where pigs live, right?
That's right.
So is it really a pig sty?
It's not really a pig sty, there are no
pigs living there, but to say that a room is
like a pig sty means that
it's very, very, very dirty.
Right.
Then it looks almost like the mud
and the dirty place where pigs live.
Exactly.
So it's saying, you're being, you're living
in a dirty room, you need to clean this.
Right.
So a room or a house
will look like a pig sty.
Now the dad is actually
making him do a lot
of work because he
says the kid is grounded.
You're grounded, you're not
allowed to play video games.
Now a parent will ground a child, it's a
verb, when the child does something bad.
So maybe the child gets
very, very bad grades at school.
And the parent says, oh,
you're grounded for one week.
That means you can't go
out, you can't play video
games, there are different
rules in every family.
But to say, you're grounded means
you're being punished for something.
Right.
So the verb is too grounded
and you can also be grounded.
And if you're grounded, you can say, I'm
sorry, I can't go out today, I'm grounded.
Exactly.
So to be grounded is
not a fun situation, but
obviously the father
is saying, listen, you're
grounded, you have
time to do all of this work.
And well, this is
something that my dad used
to say to me, well, you have
to pull your weight around here.
So you have to pull
your weight around here.
What does that mean?
To pull your weight,
well, you think about
it, if you're not carrying
yourself, someone
else is carrying you, it means that they're
doing more work than they should be.
So you're basically
being asked to do your
part, to be responsible
for yourself so that
other people like your mom and dad
don't have to be responsible for you.
Right.
So you have to help out and collaborate.
Exactly, so say, there's three
people, mom, dad, and a son.
If mom does all the
cleaning, all the cooking,
all the washing, then the other
two, they're not pulling their weight.
So she says, pull your weight, do
some cleaning, do some washing.
Right.
So if your mom cooks
and then you wash the
dishes, then you are pulling
your weight, you're helping.
You're helping out exactly.
All right.
A lot of great stuff.
Let's take a listen to the
dialogue one last time.
Kevin, what is this mess?
It looks like a pigsty in here.
Clean this up.
Okay, dad, I will do it in a minute.
Let me just finish this level of this game.
No, I said now, plus you are grounded.
You're not allowed to play video games.
I want you to make
your bed, do the laundry,
and then come downstairs
and sweep the floors.
That's so unfair.
You have to pull your weight around
here, young man, my house, my rules.
But I already mopped the floors,
dusted the furniture, and vacuum the rugs.
That's great, but you still
have work to do, so get to it.
Okay, very good.
So doing household chores, not a
fun thing, but also being grounded.
Why do we consider chores
to be kind of like a punishment?
Well, there's punishment
where you sit alone
in your room and you
think about your actions,
and then there's punishment
that's more proactive.
Right.
Mom and dad say,
"Okay, well, he's grounded.
Let's have him work.
" This didn't make
him do something.
Let's make him do something so that, you
know, we're benefiting from his punishment.
I think it's also good
when children are
grounded because it
makes them realize that, you
know, they need to help out
around the house, that it's this work.
It doesn't get done magically,
there's actually someone doing it.
Right.
And it's not like, well, in many cases, in
many countries, people will have, like, we
saw in our previous
lesson, domestic made a
cleaning lady that will
usually do everything.
So maybe the kid will become very
comfortable and not really do anything.
We're very lazy.
Very lazy.
Even worse, yes.
So I definitely remember
in my house, we had
chores, because when
it's not punishment,
when it's your parents' expectation,
normally, that's called a chore.
And they say, "Okay, Catherine,
you're chores this week.
You need to take the garbage outside.
You need to wash the dishes, and
you need to make your bed every day.
" Right.
And then maybe my
brother had to help cook and
clean the floor, mock
the floors and sweep.
So we have different chores.
And I guess this is more
common, especially if
both parents work and everyone is collaborating
or pulling their weight in the house.
And if you don't have a
cleaning lady, for example.
Exactly.
Very interesting topic.
Well, that's all the
time we have for today.
If you guys have any questions, any
comments, you can find us at EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
We'll see you guys.
Bye.